In this video, we are delighted to introduce VAD-GS, Visibility-Aware Densification for 3D Gaussian Splatting in Dynamic Urban Scenes.
Unlike object-centric settings, vehicle-mounted sensors are constrained by the driving trajectory.
Existing GS methods achieve high-quality novel view synthesis with dense training views and well-initialized point clouds.
However, their performance drops under large viewpoint changes, since photometric-based optimization fails to recover accurate geometry,
especially in dynamic urban scenes where both ego and surrounding vehicles are moving.
To address this challenge, our framework is designed as follows.
First, we analyze structural completeness for each static and dynamic instance in the reference image.
Through voxel-based visibility reasoning, our method generates a voxel distance map and a voxel index map for each view.
These maps are rasterized with z-buffering, enabling natural occlusion handling, and precise pixel-to-voxel mapping.
Each voxel corresponds to multiple observed views.
We select the most diverse supporting views that covers the object with strong stereo cues.
These views are transformed into the object’s local coordinate frame,
enabling MVS reconstruction whether the object is static or in motion.
The recovered geometry is then used as a prior for further optimization.
Extensive experiments on the Waymo and nuScenes datasets demonstrate that VAD-GS outperforms state-of-the-art 3DGS approaches,
and significantly enhances the reconstructed geometry for both static and dynamic objects.
Compared with the baseline results, the normal maps produced by VAD-GS exhibit flatter and more continuous road and wall surfaces,
while the depth maps show higher geometric consistency with fewer fragmented structures.
For scene components that are poorly initialized, such as the traffic sign in the yellow circle, which is too high to be captured by LiDAR,
our method successfully reconstructs the geometry with minimal floating artifacts, and avoids erroneously projecting white text onto the foliage behind the sign.
Thank you for watching.